or I have family there, but that a rural child lives within this shiny visage of fabulosity. (Laughter) (Applause) I invited the Motswana public into the story, my story, as a transgender person years ago, in English of course, because Setswana is a gender-neutral language and the closest we get is an approximation of "transgender." And an important part of my history got left out of that story, by association rather than out of any act of shame. "Kat" was an international superstar, a fashion and lifestyle writer, a musician, theater producer and performer -- all the things that qualify me to be a mainstream, whitewashed, new age digestible queer. Kat. Kat had a degree from one of the best universities in Africa, oh no, the world. By association, what Kat wasn't was just like the little brown-skinned children
o tengo familia allí, sino por la niña rural que vive dentro de este rostro brillante de fabulosidad. (Risas) (Aplausos) Invité al público de Motswana a la historia, mi historia, como persona transgénero hace años, en inglés, por supuesto, porque la lengua suana es de género neutral y lo más cerca que nos encontramos es una aproximación de "transgénero". Y una parte importante de mi historia quedó fuera de esa historia, por asociación y no por cualquier acto de vergüenza. "Kat" fue una superestrella internacional, una escritora de moda y estilo de vida, una música, productora de teatro e intérprete... todas las cosas que me califican para ser un ícono, emblanquecida, 'queer' de nueva generación digerible. Kat. Kat tenía un grado de una de las mejores universidades de África, oh no, del mundo. Por asociación, lo que Kat no era era como los niños pequeños de piel morena
frolicking through the streets of some incidental railway settlement like Tati Siding, or an off-the-grid village like Kgagodi, legs clad in dust stockings whose knees had blackened from years of kneeling and wax-polishing floors, whose shins were marked with lessons from climbing trees, who played until dusk, went in for supper by a paraffin lamp and returned to play hide-and-seek amongst centipedes and owls until finally someone's mother would call the whole thing to an end. That got lost both in translation and in transition, and when I realized this, I decided it was time for me to start building bridges between myselves. For me and for others to access me, I had to start indigenizing my queerness. What I mean by indigenizing is stripping away the city life film that stops you from seeing the villager within. In a time where being brown, queer, African and seen as worthy of space means being everything but rural, I fear that we're erasing the very struggles that got us to where we are now. The very first time I queered being out in a village, I was in my early 20s, and I wore a kaftan. I was ridiculed by some of my family and by strangers for wearing a dress. My defense against their comments was the default that we who don't belong, the ones who are better than, get taught, we shrug them off and say, "They just don't know enough." And of course I was wrong, because my idea of wealth of knowledge was based in removing yourself from Third World thinking and living. But it took time for me to realize that my acts of pride weren't most alive in the global cities I traipsed through, but in the villages where I speak the languages and play the games and feel most at home and I can say, "I have seen the world, and I know that people like me aren't alone here, we are everywhere." And so I used these village homes for self-reflection and to give hope to the others who don't belong. Indigenizing my queerness means bridging the many exceptional parts of myself. It means honoring the fact that my tongue can contort itself to speak the romance languages without denying or exoticizing the fact that when I am moved, it can do this: (Ululating) It means -- (Cheers) (Applause) It means branding cattle with my mother or chopping firewood with my cousins doesn't make me any less fabulous or queer, even though I'm now accustomed to rooftop shindigs, wine-paired menus and VIP lounges. (Laughter) It means wearing my pride through my grandmother's tongue, my mother's food, my grandfather's song, my skin etched with stories of falling off donkeys and years and years and years of sleeping under a blanket of stars. If there's any place I don't belong, it's in a mind where the story of me starts with the branch of me being queer and not with my rural roots. Indigenizing my queerness means understanding that the rural is a part of me, and I am an indelible part of it. Thank you. (Applause)
retozando por las calles de algún asentamiento ferroviario incidental como Tati Siding, o un pueblo fuera de la red como Kgagodi, piernas vestidas con medias de polvo cuyas rodillas se habían ennegrecido de años de arrodillarse y pulir pisos con cera, cuyas espinillas fueron marcadas con lecciones de trepar a los árboles, quién jugó hasta el anochecer entró a cenar con una lámpara de parafina y volvió a jugar a las escondidas entre ciempiés y búhos hasta que finalmente la madre de alguien terminaría todo. Eso se perdió tanto en la traducción como en la transición, y cuando me di cuenta de esto, decidí que era hora de comenzar a construir puentes entre mis propios. Para mí y para que otros me accedan, tenía que empezar a indigenizar mi rareza. Lo que quiero decir con indigenizar es quitar la película de la vida de la ciudad eso te impide ver a la aldeana dentro. En un momento donde ser marrón, 'queer', africana y visto como digno de espacio significa ser todo menos rural, me temo que estamos borrando las luchas eso nos llevó a donde estamos ahora. La primera vez que salí "queer" en un pueblo, tenía veintitantos años y vestía un kaftan. Me ridiculizaron algunos de mi familia y extraños por llevar vestido. Mi defensa contra sus comentarios fue la predeterminada que nosotros, los que no tenemos un sitio, los que somos mejores, se les enseña, a encogernos de hombros y decir: "Simplemente no saben lo suficiente". Y, por supuesto, estaba equivocada, porque mi idea de la riqueza del conocimiento se basó en alejarse del pensamiento y la vida del Tercer Mundo. Pero me llevó un tiempo darme cuenta de que mis actos de orgullo no estaban más vivos en las ciudades globales que atravesé, sino en las aldeas donde hablo los idiomas y juego y me siento como en casa y puedo decir, "He visto el mundo, y sé que las personas como yo no estamos solos aquí, estamos en todas partes". Y entonces utilicé estas casas de pueblo para la autorreflexión y dar esperanza a otros que no tienen su sitio. Indigenizando mi 'queeridad' significa unir las muchas partes excepcionales de mí misma. Significa honrar el hecho de que mi lengua puede contorsionarse para hablar las lenguas romances sin negar o hacer exótico el hecho de que cuando me muevo, puede hacer esto: (Ululante) Significa... (Aclamaciones) (Aplausos) Significa marcar el ganado con mi madre o cortar leña con mis primos no me hace menos fabulosa o rara. a pesar de que ahora estoy acostumbrada a fiestas en la azotea, menús con vino y salones VIP. (Risas) Significa llevar mi orgullo a través de la lengua de mi abuela, la comida de mi madre, la canción de mi abuelo, mi piel grabada con historias de caídas de burros y años, años y años de dormir bajo un manto de estrellas. Si hay un lugar al que no pertenezco, está en una mente donde mi historia comienza con la rama de mí siendo 'queer' y no con mis raíces rurales Indigenizar mi 'queer' significa entender que lo rural es parte de mí, y yo soy una parte indeleble de eso. Gracias. (Aplausos)